Francis Davis Millet and Millet Family
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Francis Davis Millet and Millet family papers
1858-1984 (bulk 1858-1955)
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Millet, Francis Davis and Millet family
3.25 linear feet
The Francis Davis Millet and Millet family papers measure 3.25 linear feet and are dated 1858-1984, with a few scattered early eighteenth-century items, such as legal documents and printed matter. The bulk of the materials dates from 1858 to 1955. Found are biographical materials, diaries/journals, family letters, notes and writings, art work, printed matter, miscellaneous records, and photographs documenting Millet's wide-ranging artistic and writing career and personal life, including his death aboard the Titanic. Also of interest are approximately twenty ink caricatures attributed to John Singer Sargent.
Provenance
The Francis Davis Millet and Millet family papers were received between 1974 and 1996 from several family members. Most were gifts from Dr. John A. P. Millet, son of F. D. Millet, in 1974 and 1976. In 1974, Charles S. Millet, grandnephew of F. D. Millet, donated a copy of his brief biography he wrote on F. D. Millet. Also in 1974, Mrs. William King, granddaughter of F. D. Millet gave photographs of F. D. Millet and his art work, along with various printed matter. Additional letters to F. D. Millet were given by grandson, Frank D. Millet, in 1977.
In 1987, granddaughter Joyce A. Sharpey-Schafer donated documents she had used while writing a biography of Millet. In 1996, David M. Emerson, grandnephew of F. D. Millet, donated loose sketches and miscellaneous printed matter.
In 2003, additional letters were donated by grandsons Mr. Harry Flynn and Frank D. Millet, and again in 2006 by Frank D. Millet.
Separated Material
Charles S. Millet loaned photographs, biographical information, and miscellaneous items for microfilming in 1974 on reel 849. In 1976, he loaned an album of photographs of F. D. Millet's murals in the Baltimore Customs House, with related printed matter for microfilming on reel 1080. After microfilming, the materials were returned to Charles S. Millet.
Related Material
Found within the holdings of the Archives of American Art are several collections related to Francis Davis Millet, including five letters from Millet to Miss Ward and "Ticknor" and a collection of Francis Millet Rogers research material regarding Francis Davis Millet. The Philip Martiny papers contains two group photographs that include F. D. Millet. A letter describing a visit to Millet's studio is among the William Cushing Loring Papers. The American Academy in Rome records include documents created by F. D. Millet in his capacity as Secretary from 1904-1907 and as Chief Administrator in Rome, 1911-1912.
Restrictions on Access
Use of originals requires an appointment.
Alternative Forms Available
The microfilm of this collection was digitized in 2007 and is available via the Archives of American Art's website. The collection is also available on 35 mm microfilm reels 5903-5907 at Archives of American Art offices, and through interlibrary loan.
Biographical Note
During his lifetime, Francis Davis Millet (1846-1912), always known as Frank, was a prominent artist who was well known for murals that contained exactingly accurate historical details. His broad-ranging career included work with worlds' fairs in Vienna, Chicago, Paris, and Tokyo as a juror, administrator, mural painter/decorator, or advisor. In addition, Frank Millet was a newspaper writer who published short stories and enjoyed adventures as a war correspondent during the Russo-Turkish War and in the Philippines during the Spanish American War.
Millet was among the founders of the School of the Museum of Fine Arts, Boston, and was influential in the early days of the American Federation of Arts. Millet was involved with the American Academy in Rome from its inception and served as Secretary from 1904-1911. In 1911, Millet went to Rome as Chief Administrator of the newly combined Schools of Fine Arts and Classical Studies. He died aboard the Titanic while traveling to New York City on Academy business.
Date Event
1846 born in Mattapoisett, Mass.
1864 enlisted as a private in the 60th Massachusetts Militia during Civil War, serving as a drummer; also acted as a surgical assistant to his physician father in the army of the Potomac
1869 graduated from Harvard University, where he studied modern languages and literature
1869-1870 learned lithography while working on the Boston Advertiser
1871-1872 studied at the Royal Academy of Fine Arts, Antwerp, where he won the silver medal (1871) and was awarded the gold medal (1872); traveled through Germany with 3 other American Students
1873 Secretary to Charles Francis Adams, Jr., Massachusetts' commissioner to the Vienna Exposition member of the Vienna Exposition; jury correspondent for the New York Herald and the New York Tribune; traveled through southern Europe and Turkey
1873-1874 traveled in Greece, Italy, Switzerland, and Germany
1875 toured Italy; returned to Boston and set up a studio on Tremont Street
1876 exhibited The Bay of Naples at the Philadelphia Centennial Exposition, where he represented the Boston Advertiser and was a correspondent for the American Architect and Building News; assisted John La Farge in decorating Trinity Church, Boston; founded the School of the Boston Museum of Fine Arts with La Farge and W. M. Hunt
1877 exhibited portraits of Charles Francis Adams, Jr. and Samuel L. Clements at the National Academy of Design
1877-1878 special war correspondent to the New York Herald and Times of London, and special artist to the London Graphic, reporting on the Russo-Turkish War; Russia awarded him the Cross of St. Stanislaus and the Cross of St. Anne for military advice and exceptional service (informing Russian officers of a ford that would allow them to cross into Turkey more easily) and the Iron Cross of Romania
1878 returned to Paris to paint; served on fine arts jury at the Exposition Universelle in Paris; exhibited in the Paris Salon and at the British Royal Academy
1879 married Elizabeth (Lily) Greeley Merrill in Paris; returned to the United States, settling in East Bridgewater, Mass., where he set up a studio that included an accurate reconstruction of a colonial era kitchen
1880 lectured on costumes at the School of the Museum of Fine Arts, Boston; birth of daughter, Katharine Field; became a member of the Society of American Artists; worked with Louis Comfort Tiffany on the decoration of the Seventh Regiment Armory, New York City
1881 shared studio in New York with Edwin Austin Abbey; birth of son, Edwin Abbey; commissioned by the Class of 1861 to design two windows for Harvard University Memorial Hall
1882 traveled in northern German and Scandinavia with Edwin Austin Abbey and R. Swain Gifford; elected an Associate member of the National Academy of Design
1883 traveled to England
1884 birth of Laurance, in London; settled with family in Broadway, Worcestershire (spending the winters of the next decade in New York); along with Edwin Austen Abbey, John Singer Sargent, and Alfred Parsons, he established a colony that at various times included Edwin Howland Blashfield, Lawrence Alma-Tadema, and Henry James, along with various other writers, actors, musicians
1885 traveled with Charles Francis Adams, Jr. throughout the U.S. and its territories, and to Mexico; elected a National Academician, National Academy of Design
1886 purchased "Russell House," that became his permanent home in Broadway, Worcestershire; and moved studio to "Abbot's Grange"
1887 translated "Sebastopol" by Tolstoy from French to English for publication
1888 birth of John Alfred Parsons
1889 awarded silver medal, Salon des Artistes, Paris
1890 published a collection of short stories, A Capillary Crime and Other Tales; purchased the "Abbot's Grange" that had been serving as his studio for the previous four years
1891 elected vice-president of National Academy of Design; for Harper's Magazine traveled with Alfred Parsons and Poultney Bigelow on a trip down the Danube in one-man canoes, from the Black Forest to the Black Sea (their illustrated narrative was published in the magazine, Feb.-May 1892; the following year, it appeared in book form as From the Black Forest to the Black Sea)
1892-1893 director of decorations for the White City of the World's Columbian Exposition, acting as a close advisor to the fair's architect Daniel Burnham; served on New York jury of the Columbian Exposition; once the Exposition opened, he served as Director of Functions and Ceremonies and also provided public relations and advertising services
1897 completed restoring "Abbot's Grange" to its 16th century appearance; completed lunette, Agriculture, commissioned for the Bank of Pittsburgh
1898 went to the Philippines to cover the Spanish American War as a special correspondent to Harper's Weekly, the London Times, and the New York Sun
1899 published Expedition to the Philippines, P. Bigelow, co-author
1900 appointed U. S. representative to the Paris Universal International Exposition where he was in charge of decoration of the Government Pavilion, and was a member of the Jury of Selection and the Fine Arts Jury; awarded Chevalier de la Legion of Hounneur by the French government in appreciation for his services to the Paris Exposition
1905 traveled to northwest United States, Alaska, and British Columbia; completed mural, The Treaty of the Traverse des Sioux, July 23, 1851, commissioned for the Minnesota State Capitol; became a charter member of the American Academy in Rome
1906 traveled to North Africa, Italy, and France
1907 completed mural, The Fourth Minnesota Regiment Entering Vicksburg, July 4, 1863, commissioned for the Minnesota State Capitol; completed mural, Foreman of the Grand Jury Rebuking the Chief Justice of New Jersey, 1774, commissioned for the Essex County Courthouse, Newark, New Jersey; traveled to Cuba
1908 completed The History of Shipping from the Earliest Recorded Use of Boats until the Present Time commissioned to decorate the ceiling of the Custom House, Baltimore; traveled to Japan as Special Commissioner to the proposed World's Fair in Tokyo [the fair was never held]; awarded "First Class Order of the Sacred Treasure" by the Japanese government; additional travel to Germany, Italy, Russia, Turkey, and China; elected Secretary of the American Academy in Rome; elected a member of the National Institute of Arts and Letters
1909 completed frieze of 13 panels, The History of the Settlement of Ohio, and several portraits commissioned by the Cleveland Trust Company; also responsible for the general color scheme of the building; completed frieze of 35 panels, The History of Mail Delivery, commissioned for the Post Office in the Federal Building, Cleveland; also responsible for determining the general color
1910 influential in the founding of the American Federation of Arts; served as its Secretary until his death; appointed to Federal Commission of Fine Arts; elected a member of the American Academy of Arts and Letters
1911 completed lunettes, The Repulse of the Dutch, September 3, 1609, and The Purchase of the Land, 1658, and 12 small historical panels, commissioned for the Hudson County Courthouse, Jersey City, New Jersey; also responsible for the general color scheme of the building; traveled to Panama with Lily and Mr. and Mrs. C. F. Adams, Jr.; elected Vice Chairman of the Fine Arts Committee, American Academy in Rome; moved to Rome to serve as Chief Administrator of the consolidated schools of the American Academy in Rome and the American School of Classical Studies in Rome following the death of Charles F. McKim (Millet was a charter member and had served as Secretary since its inception)
1912 died aboard the S. S. Titanic, while heading to New York City on American Academy in Rome business
Scope and Content Note
The Francis Davis Millet and Millet family papers measure 3.25 linear feet and are dated 1858-1984, with a few scattered early eighteenth-century items, such as legal documents and printed matter. The bulk of the material dates from 1858 to 1955. Found are biographical materials, diaries/journals, family letters, notes and writings, art work, printed matter, miscellaneous records, and photographs documenting Millet's wide-ranging artistic and writing career and personal life, including his death aboard the Titanic. Also of interest are approximately twenty ink caricatures attributed to John Singer Sargent.
Biographical material consists of biographical and genealogical notes; also, memorial resolutions, invitations, and programs with several related items tipped in. Diaries/journals for the period 1858-1911 (16 vols., plus excerpts and transcripts) record Civil War experiences, the Russo-Turkish War, travels throughout Europe, to the northwest United States and Alaska, the Orient, and Panama.
Letters from F. D. Millet to his family date from his years at Harvard, art training in Antwerp, residence in Italy, and service as a correspondent during the Russo-Turkish War. Millet's letters include a few received from friends and associates, original letters sent by Millet to others, along with typescript copies of incoming letters. Also included is a file of letters addressed to Millet and others concerning the purchase and restoration of the Grange, his Broadway studio. There are four letters from Millet to his girlfriend Velma Marie Morse and scattered letters to Velma's father, A.P. Morse, and Fred Chapman. Photocopies of letters from sister Kathleen Millet to her friend Margherita describe her brother's adventures during the Russo-Turkish War, and include an account of his wedding. His sister Lucia Millet's letters to her family were written while she was in England living as a member of her brother's household, and are rich with details of Frank's daily life, work, travels, friends, and the American colony in Broadway. The letters of Lily Millet consist mainly of condolence messages sent upon the death of her husband, but also include letters from Samuel L. Clemens, Henry James, Ellen Terry [Carew], Charles Dudly Warner, her children, and others.
Included in the collection are Millet's extensive research notes about costumes and artifacts of various historical periods and locations that served as reference for details in his murals. Also included are his notebooks about Italian art, Bulgarian history and costume, and the Philippines. Writings by Millet consist of articles, short stories, lectures and speeches. Writings about him include texts by various relatives (all but one are unpublished). The most extensive written piece is by niece Hilda Millet Booth and son John [Albert] Parsons Millet, and is accompanied by early drafts, notes, and related correspondence.
Art work by Millet includes twelve volumes of sketchbooks dating from his student days in Antwerp through 1896, along with loose sketches, drawings, and two watercolors. Most were executed while traveling, and include landscapes, building, and local peoples. Works by other artists include 20 caricatures drawn in ink, attributed to John Singer Sargent.
Among the printed matter are newspaper articles by F. D. Millet, along with clippings about or mentioning him, reproductions, exhibition catalogs and announcements. Of interest are Vienna Exposition memorabilia, and a full length biography, Soldier of Fortune: F. D. Millet, 1846-1912 by granddaughter Joyce A. Sharpey-Schafer. Miscellaneous records include drawings sketches, notes, printed matter, and photographs relating to the Abbot's Grange in Broadway that served as Millet's studio.
Photographs of people include F. D. Millet, his father Asa Millet with granddaughter Kate, and Mary Anderson. Photographs of works of art are by Millet and other artists.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into eight series:
Series 1: Biographical material, circa 1864-1934 (Box 1; 6 folders; Reel 5903)
Series 2: Diaries/Journals of Francis Davis Millet, 1858-1911 (Box 1; 0.5 linear ft.; Reels 5903-5904)
Series 3: Letters, 1867-1915, undated (Boxes 1-2; 0.5 linear ft.; Reel 5904)
Series 4: Notes and Writings, 1891-1970, undated (Box 3; 1.0 linear ft.; Reels 5904-5906)
Series 5: Art Work, 1872-1908, undated (Box 4; 0.5 linear ft.; Reels 5906-5907)
Series 6: Printed Matter, 1764-1984, undated (Box 4; 0.25 linear ft.; Reel 5907 and unfilmed)
Series 7: Miscellaneous Records, 1724-1897, undated(Box 4; 7 folders; Reel 5907)
Series 8: Photographs, circa 1883-circa 1910, undated (Box 4; 7 folders; Reel 5907)
Index Terms
This collection is indexed in the online catalog of the Archives of American Art under the following terms:
Subjects:
Abbey, Edwin Austin, 1852-1911; James, Henry, 1843-1916; Sargent, John Singer, 1856-1925; Titanic (Steamship)
Subjects-Topical:
Painting -- American; Mural painting and decoration; Painters; Art -- Study and teaching; Artists' studios; Russo-Turkish War, 1877-1878
Subjects-Geographical:
United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865
Types of Materials:
Photographs; Sketchbooks; Diaries; Travel journals; Works of art
Names:
Booth, Hilda Millet; Millet, John A. P. (John Alfred Parsons), 1888-1976; Sharpey-Schafer, Joyce A.
Series Descriptions/Container Listing
- Biographical Material, circa 1864-1934, Series 1:; (Box 1; 6 folders; Reel 5903)
  The biographical notes consist of typescript copies of entries about Millet that appeared in various publications. Of particular interest is the memorial volume probably compiled by J. B. Pine. Consisting mainly of printed items, it includes four tipped in photographs (portraits of F. D. Millet circa 1912, as a Civil War drummer boy, circa 1862, and two views of a bust of Millet by Albin Polasek) and three tipped in letters (two from Millet to Pine, and one from Albin Polasek to Pine regarding his portrait bust of Millet).
  Miscellaneous printed material in this series consists of a copy of the program, Francis Davis Millet Memorial Meeting, The American Federation of Arts, Washington, D. C., 1912, with texts of addresses by Elihu Root, Henry Cabot Lodge, Charles Francis Adams, and Charles D. Wolcott and other tributes. Also included is the July 1912 issue of Art and Progress devoted to Francis Davis Millet featuring articles by his brother-in-law Sylvester Baxter, William A. Coffin, Edwin Howland Blashfield, Carroll Beckwith, George W. Maynard, and a notice about the Francis Davis Millet Memorial Chair of Fine Arts in the American Academy in Rome. Also bound with this volume is the 1912 issue of the Bulletin of the Metropolitan Museum of Art (Vol. 7, No. 6) containing the Museum's Francis Davis Millet memorial resolution.
  - Biographical Notes about F. D. Millet, circa 1894-1912, undated (Reel 5903, Frame 12-28)
  - Genealogy, 1938, undated (Reel 5903, Frame 29-35)
  - Memorial Program and Related Items, circa 1864-1912, (1 volume) (Reel 5903, Frame 36-104)
  - Memorial Programs, Notices and Invitations, 1912-1934 (Reel 5903, Frame 105-111)
  - Memorial Resolutions, 1912, (2 folders) (Reel 5903, Frame 112-175)
  - Official Papers concerning Millet's status as a Correspondent, Russo-Turkish War, 1877 (Reel 5903, Frame 176-187)
  - Official Papers concerning Travel in Eastern Europe, 1872-1873 (Reel 5903, Frame 188-191)
  - Royal Academy of Fine Arts, Antwerp, Student Registration Cards, 1871-1872 (Reel 5903, Frame 192-196)
  - Will, 1885 (Reel 5903, Frame 197-198)
- Diaries/Journals of F. D. Millet, 1858-1911, Series 2:; (Box 1; 0.5 linear ft.; Reels 5903-5904)
  Found here are 16 volumes of diaries and/or journals for the period 1858-1911 that record Millet's Civil War experiences, the Russo-Turkish War, and his travels throughout Europe, the northwest United States and Alaska, the Orient, and Panama.
  - January 1-July 23, 1858 (Reel 5903, Frame 200-264)
  - "Civil War Diary," (in four parts, includes partial transcripts), 1864-1865 (Reel 5903, Frame 265-309)
  - Trip to the Rhine, September 11-21, 1871, (2 volumes) (Reel 5903, Frame 310-358)
  - Trip to Holland, March 30, 1872 (Reel 5903, Frame 359-406)
  - Trip to Southern Europe and Turkey, October 9, 1873-1874 (Reel 5903, Frame 407-519)
  - Trip Throughout Italy, January 27-June 27, 1875, (2 volumes) (Reel 5903, Frame 520-615)
  - Russo-Turkish War and Trip to Sweden, June 5, 1877, June 18-July 29, 1882 (Reel 5903, Frame 616-718)
  - "Diary of a Trip to the West," 1885 (Reel 5903, Frame 719-897)
  - Canoe Trip Down the Danube, June 20-October 26, 1891, (2 volumes) (Reel 5903, Frame 898-1044)
  - "Trip to the North West and Alaska," 1905 (Reel 5903, Frame 1045-1145)
  - "Trip to the Orient," September 1-November 24, 1908, (3 volumes) (Reel 5903, Frame 1146-1452)
  - "Diary of Trip to Panama," March 6-30, 1911 (Reel 5904, Frame 13-107)
- Letters, 1867-1915, undated, Series 3:; (Boxes 1-2; 0.5 linear ft.; Reel 5904)
  According to granddaughter Joyce A. Sharpey-Schafer, Lily Millet destroyed her husband's correspondence and was unwilling to cooperate with biographers. However, many of F. D. Millet's letters to his family survive for the period 1867-1879. The letters include a small number of original letters received by Millet from friends and associates augmented by typescript copies of incoming letters and a fairly large number of collected original letters sent by Millet, including two from John Singer Sargent. The sources of this material are for the most part unknown, though a few of the typescript copies are identified as coming from collections at the Library of Congress. The original outgoing letters may have been gathered by John A. P. Millet during the course of researching and writing his father's biography.
  The letters discuss Millet's travels, education, journalistic and art career, art sales and commissions, and the activities of artist friends, family members, and acquaintances. One folder of letters, addressed to F. D. Millet and others, is about the purchase and restoration of the Grange, his Broadway studio. There are four letters from Millet to his girlfriend Velma Marie Morse and scattered letters to Velma's father, A.P. Morse, and Fred Chapman.
  Typescript copies and a photocopy of four letters from sister Kathleen Millet to her friend Margherita, 1878-1879, are from an unknown source. Written from Paris, they mention Frank's "decoration for gallantry" during the Russo-Turkish War, and detailed information about his arrival home, describing his adventures, and an account of his wedding.
  Letters to Lily Millet are from Samuel L. Clemens, Henry James, Ellen Terry [Carew], Charles Dudley Warner, the Millet children, and other friends and acquaintances. The bulk of the letters are condolence messages to the family upon Millet's death aboard the Titanic in 1912.
  The letters Lucia Millet wrote to her family are mostly from the period when she was in England, living as a member of her brother's Broadway household. She describes moving into Farnham House, Broadway, and their later, permanent move to Russell House. Scattered throughout the letters are frequent mentions of Frank's activities, his work, travels, friends (including John Singer Sargent, Edwin Austin Abbey, and Henry James), and the American colony in Broadway. Of particular interest are references to Sargent sending lilies for the garden, and sewing white dresses for the girls to wear in Sargent's painting (Carnation, Lily, Lily, Rose). The letters also recount trips to London where she visited Sargent's and Whistler's studios.
  Attached to many of the letters are brief notes made by John A. P. Millet.
  - F. D. Millet (Reel 5904)
    - To Family, 1867-1875, undated (Reel 5904, Frame 109-234)
    - Collected Letters, 1874-1912, undated (Reel 5904, Frame 235-431)
    - Collected Letters, A.P. Morse and Velma Marie Morse, 1874-1879 (Box 1, Folder 29)